Guide to the Elizabeth Gurley Flynn Photographs PHOTOS.018
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn Photographs
1895-1967
PHOTOS.018
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.5 linear feet
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn (1890-1964) was a leading Irish-American Communist, feminist, labor organizer, orator, and campaigner for civil liberties. While barely in her twenties, she became an organizer for the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) and a leader of some of its most famous strikes. She was a founder of the American Civil Liberties Union, and also worked to try to save the celebrated imprisoned anarchists Sacco and Vanzetti from execution. In 1936, she joined the Communist Part of the United States (CPUSA), in short order becoming a member of its Central Committee, and later of its Political Bureau, and finally Chair, in 1961-1964. During these years she wrote a bi-weekly column "Life of the Party" for the Party's newspaper, the Daily Worker, wrote an autobiography, ran for political office, and attended international conferences. In 1952, her leadership role with the CPUSA resulted in her trial under the Smith Act, and subsequently her conviction and incarceration in a Federal prison for 28 months. She died in Moscow in September, 1964. The approximately 239 photographs in this collection--almost exclusively black and white prints-span the 1890s to the 1960s. They document not only Flynn's public role as a revolutionary and spokesperson for labor and civil liberties, but also her private roles as mother, lover, and family member.
ca. 239 items (3x2, 5x7, 8x10; b&w)
Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley
Provenance
Separated from the Papers of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn (Tamiment 118).
Access Restrictions
Because this is a heavily used collection and because of preservation concerns, researchers are requested to consult a complete set of photocopies before looking at the original photographs. Rights to reproduce all photographs require the permission of the CPUSA and the Estate of Elizabeth Gurley Flynn.
Historical/Biographical Note
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn (1890-1964), was a leading Irish-American Communist, socialist, feminist, labor organizer, orator, and campaigner for civil liberties. Raised by socialist and Irish nationalist parents, she gave her first speech at the age of fifteen. She became an organizer for the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) and while aiding the Western Federation of Miners was briefly married to Jack Jones, the father of her son Fred, born in 1910. During her involvement in the IWW's Lawrence, Massachusetts textile strike of 1912 she met and fell in love with anarchist organizer Carlo Tresca, with whom she lived for the next twelve years. In 1917 she founded and chaired the International Liberty Defense League (later the Workers Liberty Defense Union) until 1924, when the International Labor Defense was formed. She was also an officer of the Garland Fund, and a founder of the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU). After the execution of Sacco and Vanzetti in 1927, Flynn fell seriously ill and spent nine years in Oregon where she lived with feminist activist Dr. Marie Equi. In 1936 Flynn returned to New York and joined the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA), in short order becoming a member of its Central Committee, and later its Political Bureau, and finally Chair, 1961-1964. During these years she wrote a bi-weekly column "Life of the Party" for the Daily Worker, wrote an autobiography, (variously, I Speak My Own Piece and The Rebel Girl), ran for political office, attended international conferences, was expelled from the ACLU in 1940 for her Communist Party membership. In 1952, her leadership role with the CPUSA resulted in her trial under the Smith Act and in her conviction and imprisonment for 28 months in prison under the Smith Act. Upon her release, Flynn wrote a prison memoir, published as The Alderson Story. She died in Moscow in September, 1964.
Scope and Content Note
The photographs in this collection document not only Flynn's public role as a spokesperson for labor and civil liberties but also her more private roles as mother and family member. More than half of the photographs are images of Flynn and her family and friends. Included are several hand-inscribed portraits from Flynn, her son's high school graduation photograph inscribed to Flynn. Many of the early portraits are original albumen prints.
The approximately 239 photographs in this collection--almost exclusively black and white prints-span the 1890s to the 1960s. They document not only Flynn's public role as a revolutionary and spokesperson for labor and civil liberties, but also her private roles as mother, lover, and family member. More than half of the images are of Flynn and her family and friends. The remainder document her work with the Industrial Workers of the World and the Communist Party of the United States (CPUSA), and include shots of Flynn at two of the IWW's major strikes--the 1912 Lawrence, Massachusetts, textile workers' strike, and the 1913 silkworkers' strike in Paterson, New Jersey--and of her 1961 trip to the Soviet Union as Chair of the CPUSA. Individuals pictured include leading American Communists and IWW leaders.
Besides numerous portraits of Flynn herself, persons specifically pictured include, but are not limited to, her family, including mother Annie Flynn, son Fred Flynn, sister Kathie Flynn, father Thomas Flynn, and one of Flynn's nieces, Roberta Bobba; IWW comrades, Carlo Tresca, Joseph Ettor, Arturo Gionvanitti, Frank Little, and William "Big Bill" Haywood; leading American Communists and CPUSA friends and acquaintances, "Mother" Ella Reeve Bloor, Ann Burlech, Claudia Jones, Benjamin Davis, Eugene Dennis, Michael Gold, Gus Hall, Grace Hutchins, Bill McKie, Steve Nelson, William L Patterson, Pettis Perry, Irving Slavin, and Carl Winter. Others include Helen Keller, Kate Richards O 'Hare, Hannah Sheehy Skeffington, Helen Stassona; Mary Heaton Vorse; Judge O.N. Hilton, Marie Equi, and a group portrait (ca. 1906/1907) of the Harlem Socialist Club.
Arrangement
Arrangement is topical.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Container list
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn Papers (Tamiment 118).
Roberta Bobba–Peter Martin Photographs (Photographs 55)
Louis Weinstock Photographs (Photographs 77).
Bloor, Ella Reeve, 1862-1951; Bobba, Roberta -- |v Portraits; Burlech, Ann--Portraits.; Communist Party of the United States of America. -- |v Pictorial works; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964 -- |v Portraits; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961. -- |v Portraits; Equi, Marie -- |v Portraits; Ettor, Joseph J. -- |v Portraits; Flynn, Anne Gurley--Portraits.; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley -- |v Portraits; Flynn, Fred, 1910-1940 -- |v Portraits; Flynn, Katherine. -- |v Portraits; Flynn, Thomas--Portraits.; Giovannitti, Arturo M., 1884-1959 -- |v Portraits; Gold, Michael, 1893-1967 -- |v Portraits; Hall, Gus; Harlem Socialist Club.; Haywood, Big Bill, 1869-1928. -- |v Portraits; Hilton, O. N.--Portraits.; Hutchins, Grace, 1885-; Industrial Workers of the World. -- |v Pictorial works; Jones, Claudia, 1915-1964. -- |v Portraits; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968. -- |v Portraits; Little, Frank, d. 1917; McKie, Bill --Portraits.; O'Hare, Kate Richards, 1877-1948. -- |v Portraits; Patterson, William L. (William Lorenzo), 1890-1980; Perry, Pettis.; Skeffington, Hannah Sheehy--Portraits.; Slavin, Irving--Portraits.; Stassona, Helen--Pictorial works.; Tresca, Carlo, 1879-1943. -- |v Pictorial works; Vorse, Mary Heaton, 1874-1966; Winter, Carl. -- |v Portraits; Black-and-white photographs.; Lawrence (Mass.) |v Pictorial works.; Lowell (Mass.) |v Pictorial works.; May Day (Labor holiday) |z United States |v Pictorial works.; Negatives (photographic); Paterson (N.J.) |v Pictorial works.; Silk Workers' Strike, Paterson, N.J., 1913 |v Pictorial works.; Strikes and lockouts |x Textile industry |z United States.; Strikes and lockouts |z United States |v Pictorial works.; Textile Workers' Strike, Lawrence, Mass., 1912 |v Pictorial works.; Textile Workers' Strike, Lowell, Mass., 1912 |v Pictorial works.; Washington Square Park (New York, N.Y.) |v Pictorial works.; Women communists |z United States |v Portraits.; Women labor leaders |z United States |v Portraits.; Women political activists |z United States |v Portraits.; Women radicals |z United States |v Portraits.
- Container list
  - Portraits of E.G. Flynn, ca. 1905-1930 (26 items) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portraits of E.G. Flynn, ca. 1939-1963 (26 items) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family photographs, ca. 1912-1938 (33 items) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family photographs (parents, sisters, Harlem Socialist club, sister Kathie's daughter and family), ca. 1895-1960 (37 items) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Early work with the IWW, ca. 1909-1934. (Butte, Montana, Lawrence Strike, Paterson Strike, Lowell, Massachusetts Strikers, Ettor and Giovanitti, Haywood, Tresca, speech in Seattle, Tampa May Day, Mesabi Range, Mary Heaton Vorse) (29 items) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Work with the CPUSA, ca. 1937-1963 (36 items) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Trip to Russia, ca. 1960-61 (41 items), ca.1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Other people and unidentified photos, ca. 1918- 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oversize negatives and 35mm negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - new (Box 1, Folder 10)